Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972 UA.90.4.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Tektite Symposium, 2nd International held at University of Pittsburgh, September 5-7, 1963; Proceedings in Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta; Journal of the Geochemical Society, June 1964; position inquiry; "Teaching Program of the Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences" pamphlet describing staff and courses; colloquium announcements; Cooperation Program Pitt-CIT; Progress on Oceanography Program; Latin American programs of the department and GSPIA.
- Earth and Planetary Science (Box 5, Folder 38)
  General Policy Statement; Cooperative Program Pitt-CIT; Oceanography Project; Publication "Scientific and Technical Personnel in Oceanography"; draft of "An Historical Review and a Statement of Position"; "Oceanography, the Institute and the Department" paper; correspondence.
- Earth and Planetary Science - "Status Report on the Program of Oceanography" by A.F Frederickson, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  Correspondence on new administrative arrangement; new courses and programs; Langley Hall space locations for department; staff meeting, May 20, 1965; floor space plan 5th floor Langley and 1st, 4th, and 6th floors SRCC Building.
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  Correspondence on Departmental Advisory Committee survey for name change to Earth Science; general policy statement and review, September 1966; Oceanography equipment purchased under Scaife grant and in personal possession of Dr. Frederickson and used at Virgin Gorda site; Correspondence on land at Virgin Gorda; Correspondence on return of grant funds to Scaife Foundation -final settlement to be made when Virgin Gorda site sold; course information, Spring 1966-1967; proposed program with University of Newcastle; equipment donated by Gulf Research; report of faculty positions filled, post-doctorals and graduate students.
- Geology - Search for Head, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  C.E. Prouty to Dean Lauffer about courses and research in Geology, August 16, 1957; Prouty resignation effective September 1, 1957; Lauffer to Litchfield on Geology Department programs and nominees for head, October 13, 1958; Lauffer correspondence with Columbia University, Harvard, MIT, Johns Hopkins, Princeton, University of California and Yale about search for head.
- Geology- Search for Head, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  Correspondence with nominees and curriculum vital.
- Geology - Search for Head, Candidates, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Geology - Search for Head, Candidates, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Geology - Search for Head, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  Correspondence with and concerning Clarence Allen, Aureal T. Cross, Arman F. Frederickson, and Richard H. Jahns.
- Geology - Search for Head, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  Correspondence. with and concerning W.C. Hrumbein, Thane McCulloh, Um. T. Pecora, Edwin Roedder, Lawrence L. Sloss, and Edward Zeller.
- Mathematics, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Staff reaching age 70; use of space in Cathedral of Learning; listing of courses for 1958/1959 bulletin; J.S. Taylor, head, memo on low salaries of Mathematics faculty; "The Improvement of the Teaching of Science and Mathematics in the Elementary Schools" booklet published by DePauw University, 1958; list of department needs for next 5 to 10 years; program of Allegheny Mountain Section, Mathematics Association of America meeting, April 1960; Taylor to Lauffer about crucial situation of faculty resigning plus "An Analysis of the Mathematics Situation"; graduate student participation in planning; grade distribution on advanced calculus; attempt to analyze grade distributions in mathematics; schedule of courses, Spring 1959/1960; Learning Resources Institute Continental Classroom Plans, 1960/1961.
- Mathematics, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  Evaluation of Guenther EMDE made by Lauffer for U.S. Joint Intelligence Objectives Agency; conditions on 4th floor of Cathedral of Learning causing disturbances in Math offices; teaching help from Electrical Engineering Department; assignment of classrooms in Logan Armory; splitting of lecture and recitation for Math 23; consideration of a math course for social scientists; suggestions for Mathematics based on Chancellor's Convocation address on "Work and Survival"; correspondence about search for Mathematics chairman.
- Mathematics, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  Colloquium announcements; NSF summer fellowships for secondary school teachers and Pitt courses offered; estimate of number of graduate students 1961/1962; faculty salaries; correspondence on mathematics course for social scientists and sequence proposed by E. Fels; document by Dr. Fels on the Mathematics department and the training of statisticians; schedule of courses, Winter 1961/1962; report by J.C. Knipp on the Doctor of Arts Degree Conference, October 1961; scheduling of classes for 1962/1963; request for space in Langley Hall.
- Mathematics, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  Correspondence on library budget for Mathematics; memo on operation of the Math department; "University Policy Regarding The Mathematics Department" prepared by Professor Mario Benedicty; agenda for Planning Committee meetings, January-April 1963; draft of letter on Math department and lack of chairman to Chancellor from E.H. Fels and members of The Interdisciplinary Committee and reply from Dr. Peake; recruiting letters from Fels to mathematicians in Europe; plans for securing research support; proposed joint program with CIT; proposed new course "Stability Theory of Differential Equations"; request that Dr. Knipp visit Lima, Ohio to evaluate the teaching of Dr. William F. Steele; teaching of probability and statistics; questionnaire sent to other departments regarding mathematics needs; grading in Math department; report to the Curriculum Committee, December 1962; Course schedules, 1962-1963; breakdown of graduate students in Math; breakdown of teaching loads; move some Math offices to Langley Hall; memo on space needs and request for space in Schenley Hall; floor plans Schenley Hall 6th and 7th floors.
- Mathematics, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  Colloquium notices; news release on department reorganization, August 26, 1963; plans to recruit faculty from the Math Group of Research Institute for Advanced Study, Baltimore; plans to teach Math 80; Joint Pitt-Tech program in mathematics; complaints about teaching; statistics of attendance by major departments; course outlines for Math 155-156; program in statistics; duties of faculty members, 1963/1964.
- Mathematics, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  Colloquium notices; press release announcing transfer of major part of Mathematics group at Research Institute for Advanced Studies, Baltimore, to Brown University; joint program Pitt-Tech to be kept informal; teaching of Math 21; math department recommendations for Interdepartmental Ph.D. programs; program in statistics; request for more space in Schenley Hall; teaching schedule of graduate assistants and TFs, Fall 1964/1965; DNS Building occupant survey; "Langley Hall Package Deal" about space, October 9, 1964; televised course in Mathematics; "Proposal to WIIC, Channel 11, Telecast of Modern Mathematics."
- Mathematics, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  Changes in the Graduate Mathematics Curriculum effective Fall 1965; potential support from Ford Foundation for developing Division of Mathematical Sciences; colloquium notices; minutes of the Inter-School Mathematics Committee Meeting, November 5, 1965 and March 4, 1966; description of probability and statistics courses; pilot project experiment in teaching of large classes; report from Dr. C.Y. Chao on how to teach Math 30 so freshman will understand; "Graduate Study in Mathematics at the University of Pittsburgh, 1965-66" brochure.
- Mathematics, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  Colloquium notices; announcement of Math 160 offered jointly by Department of Biostatistics and Math; mathematics problem for Engineering students-grading and course content; request for more space in Schenley Hall; "Graduate Study in Mathematics at the University of Pittsburgh, 1967-68" brochure.
- Mathematics (Box 7, Folder 56)
  Remote consoles and the Computer Science Interaction Committee (DNS); material on the development of The Division of Mathematical Sciences; draft of "Division of Mathematical Sciences: a Ten Year Development Plan"; drafts about the subject of a Department of Statistics; requests from Engineering Dean Hollscher for syllabi for certain courses in Math and Chemistry.
- Microbial and Molecular Biology, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  Material on microbiology group of Biology Department which is to be established as a new academic department; Biophysics Department adopts motion to join the new department; status report on the department listing faculty, staff, students, and courses.
- Microbiology, 1964-1967 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  Draft proposal for graduate degree program in Microbiology, May 26, 1964; approval by department and sectional representatives, June 11, 1964; "Doctor of Philosophy Program Microbiology, University of Pittsburgh" brochure; correspondence on Microbiology as a separate department; job descriptions for office personnel; floor plan, 3rd floor Langley Hall.
- Physics, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  Colloquium announcements; report by Norman Austern enumerating activities during leave of absence, 1957-1958; request and approval for B.L. Cohen to act as a consultant to the cyclotron nuclear physics group at Oak Ridge National Laboratory; report requested by T.M. Donahue in application for a Fulbright exchange grant; proposal for attracting two of the world's first flight physicists to the faculty; "A Plan for the Development of the Physics Faculty," October 1958; restructuring of physics courses to fit into the trimester plan requested by engineering Dean Fitterer; University of Pittsburgh cooperating with AACTE and NBC in offering Atomic Age Physics as a credit course; move from Cathedral of Learning to Clapp Hall; scale drawing #3368 of "Plan for Changes in Storage Space to Move Physics Dept. Lectures to Clapp Hall Auditorium"; Old Mellon Institute space assigned to Physics and to the Radiation Laboratory; blue print of Clapp Hall #3240 as of March 1, 1956; floor plan of Old Mellon Institute 2nd floor.
- Physics, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  Colloquium notices; correspondence; inquiries about employment; course listings, Fall 1959-1960; School of Engineering requests for evening Physics courses; grade distributions.
- Physics, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  "Opportunity in Physics: The Undergraduate Program in Physics at the University of Pittsburgh" brochure distributed to high school students in a seven-state area; proposals for changing name of Old Mellon Institute; space in OMI and Thaw Hall; proposal to estimate undergraduate atomic physics lab, 1959, and correspondence Scaife Foundation for funding, 1960, with OMI floor plans OMI.; "Graduate Work in Physics at the University of Pittsburgh" brochure, November 1960.
- Physics, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  Colloquium notices; eight Pitt physicists attend International Congress on Nuclear Structure at Queen's University, Kinston, Ontario; two faculty accepting positions elsewhere; Physics Engineering curriculum, offering of credit courses in The Continental Classroom NBC-TV program; invitation to lecture and tours of the Physics Research Laboratories for high school students; space question.
- Physics, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  Colloquium notices and seminars; list of visitors in Department of Physics; report by the Pittsburgh Study Group for Nuclear Info entitled "Fallout Protection - What to know and do about nuclear attack"; six Pitt physicists invited to Rutherford Jubilee Conference on Nuclear Physics held at Manchester, England; class schedule, Winter 1961/1962; physics enrollment, 1960/1961; requests for additional space in Old Mellon Institute; Spectroscopy Laboratory recommendations; correspondence on costs of equipment; "Future Plans for the Physics Library" paper; Halliday letter to Lauffer on teaching of applied physics.
- Physics, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  Colloquium notices; copy of report by Pittsburgh Study Group for Nuclear Information: "The Effects of Nuclear War on the Pittsburgh Area" and summary; library problems concerning journal subscriptions; Quehanna Nuclear Reactor; Triga reactor correspondence and publications furnished by General Dynamics Corporation which describe applications of the reactor.
- Physics, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  Distribution of courses in undergraduate program; course offerings, Spring 1963; Dean Halliday's memo to department chairman suggesting brochures be developed for recruitment and research proposals with examples; renovations needed for magnet installation on 4th floor of Old Mellon Institute; Thaw Hall #304 designed as shelter from Gamma radiation; History requests relinquishing of book funds for History of Science materials.
- Physics, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 66)
  Colloquium notices; minutes of Tumble Run Conference on the Space Program, July 9, 1963; Douglas Aircraft Company and University of Pittsburgh agreement on Aerial Photography of The Eclipse of the Quiet Sun by Airplane over Northern Canada on July 20, 1963; staff meeting agenda, September 17, 1963; Triga reactor; grade distributions of engineering students; O.H. Blackwood Memorial award and A.G. Worthing award; Physics major undergraduate courses; graduate student group solves problem and submits results for publication.
- Physics, 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  Physics Department open house for high school physics teachers and students; listing of department personnel, Spring 1963/1964; wind tunnel in Engineering Hall; renovation of Old Mellon Institute; electronics shop serves DNS; Professors Fite and Brackman invited by NASA to submit bid for a contract to build some space hardware which involves use of university facilities; final report on disposition of graduate students applications for 1964/1965; letters on Douglas Davids for teaching in Physics; listing of applications for Postdoctoral for 1964/1965; Galileo celebration 1564/1964; analysis of physics courses for engineering students.
- Physics, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  Visiting lecturers; notice competitive physics tests; colloquium and seminar notices; correspondence on high energy accelerator; memo and notice of Physics 81; letter about Physics 780; Physics 17; "Graduate Study in Physics" brochure, 1965; correspondence on open house; memo on Physics 83; proposal for undergrad curriculum; memos on physical plant; letter to Van Dusen from Halliday about spinoff; memo on publications; excerpt from executive committee meeting on new name for Old Mellon Institute; memo on Pitt-AVCO; list of admission for grad study, 1964/1965; memo about librarian; publicity notice of new high energy faculty; proposed fundamental particle physics group; application for post-doctoral fellowships.
- Physics, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  Seminar and colloquium notices; correspondence on high energy accelerator; newsletter #1, 1966; memos on cooperation in finding class space; correspondence on physical plant; summary of meeting in Minneapolis on intro physics courses; clipping on improving teaching; correspondence about dedication of Van de Graaff Lab; correspondence about naming buildings; letter about 89th Congress HR6666 to allow Pitt to import spectrometer duty free.
- Physics, 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  List of Physics colloquia and seminars, 1966; correspondence on Master Plan for Higher Education; disposition of graduate student applications; letter on expansion into Engineering Hall; picture of Physics complex; seminar notices; descriptions of several physics course; memo on enrollment by General Studies students; list of grad student applications; correspondence on Western Pennsylvania Academic Council on Problems of War and Peace (WPAC) and using university mail to distribute literature; correspondence on graduate assistants and wage tax; proposal for science education program; invitation from Juniata College for Physics Consultant; letter about Dr. Castle, Westinghouse Labs; correspondence on travel arrangements to USSR conference; correspondence on new name for Old Mellon Institute; letter to Dean regarding physics problem in his textbook; correspondence on reports and publications to NASA; memo of meeting to discuss financial support for department; equipment requirements; tabulation of graduate students from 1963/1964-1968/1969; plan for improvement of teaching physics in secondary schools; list of new graduate assistants and fellows, 1967/1968; new doctoral personnel for 1967/1968.
- Psychology, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  Colloquium notices; list of professional activities, appointments and promotions; program for conference on experimental psychiatry; correspondence on department operating clinic (eg. student counseling); letter of commendation from American Psychological Association; correspondence on relationship between Psychology department and psychology training at WPIC; conflict between department and Education psychology; current trends conference, March 12, 1959; memo on program in social psychology; correspondence about department personnel; space and equipment needs; memos on student advisors; student complaints; funds received for psychological testing; correspondence on reorganizing office of education research; 5-yr. budget estimated for department; "Tribute to College Professor" article.
- Psychology, 1959-1961 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  Colloquium notices 1959/1960; letter on publication of current trend lectures; correspondence about problems with social psychology program and Psychology department under Natural Sciences; analysis of staff needs; spring 1960 schedule; joint program in biophysics and psychology at University of Washington; space problems; annual report to American Psychological Association; seminar roster, HE 210, 1960; colloquium notices, 1960/1961; report from department; summary of financial training support; memo on inter-department program in social psychology; correspondence on seminar in counseling at University of Pittsburgh Johnstown; problem with Department of Education about psychology courses; notice of summer workshop in programmed instruction.
- Psychology, 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  Report from Department; Middle States Association evaluation of Department; colloquium notices; Social Psychology Committee meeting minutes; teaching schedules, 1962/1963; space needs; policies governing regular fellowships of Public Health Society, 1962; chart showing interrelationship between Psychology and other departments; description of UCLA Psychology Department.
- Psychology, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  Report from American Psychological Association evaluating clinical psychology program; colloquium notices; organization chart; graduate admissions report; memo on joint participation with Dentistry; graduate program in Social Psychology; scheduling problems; teaching schedule; space problems; memo on department goals; correspondence about graduate program in college teaching.
- Psychology, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  Correspondence on evaluation of clinical psychology; evaluation of social psychology; reorganization of Psychology department; colloquium notices; memos on scheduling classes; newspaper clippings on cheating incident; description of research programs; plan for remote console system for computer use in psychology.
- Psychology, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  Correspondence about petty cash fund for department; American Psychological Association approves clinical psychology program; colloquium and seminar notices; Dr. Allen Fisher's position paper on physiological psychology and proposal to teach; undergraduate student Sandra Walker presents paper at American Psychology Association; letter on cooperation with VA hospital; correspondence on need for additional staff in Educational Psychology, 1967; Allen Fisher proposal for a Brain-Behavior program including NIH funding, 1966; correspondence on strengthening Social Psychology program; letter from Educational Testing Society, Princeton, N.J., about Pitt participating in developing an examination, 1967; Graduate Study in Psychology brochure; letter praising students who participated in Pittsburgh Psychological Association meeting, 1967; correspondence about releasing space in Bellefield Building; staff needs projections for 1971/1972.
- Psychology - Testing Service, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  Reviews of recent books by Dr. Glaser; manual for student and counselor to understand testing; "Performance of Liberal Arts Students as measured by Grad Record Examination Area Tests" by Eloise France, January 1960; "A Descriptive Study of 1958 and 1959 Entering Freshman Classes of University of Pittsburgh in Terms of Selection and Placement Measurements" by Lawrence Fox, May 1960; Graduate Records Exam Special Report by Educational Testing Service, 1960; SAT scores of Class of 1960.
- Psychology - Testing Service, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  "Some comparisons of aptitude and achievement test results for 1959 and 1960 entering freshman classes at University of Pittsburgh" by Phoebe Suica, 1961; "A Brief Report on the Revised UPE" by Robert Willoughby, 1961; Spring testing schedule; "A Report of the Performance of University of Pittsburgh Seniors and Sophomores on area tests of Graduate records examination" by University Testing Service.
- Psychology - Testing Service, 1962-1967 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  Correspondence with Dr. Glaser on establishing a center for Research on Learning and Instruction; draft for proposed center (became Learning Research and Development Center); "Freshman Placement Series, Mathematics 1963" by Mohiuddin Ahmed, 1964; memo to Chancellor on proposed establishment of Bureau of Psychological Services; memo on the functions of a testing service, 1967.
- Radiation Laboratory, 1946-1967 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  Newspaper article about opening of lab, February 18, 1947; correspondence on space needs, 1959; tax and tuition status for research assistants; correspondence about cost estimate of building an addition to lab, 1960; correspondence on commercial use of radiation lab; agreement between Western N.Y. Nuclear Research Center, Inc. and Nuclear Science and Engineering Corporation, 1965; proposal to turn cyclotron over to Medical School.
- Admissions, 1961-1967 (Box 9, Folder 81)
- Alumni (see also Development, Alumni activities), 1959-1964 (Box 10, Folder 82)
  List of University of Pittsburgh grads listed in Biological Sciences volume of American Men of Science, 1955; nominations of distinguished alumni for honorary degrees; correspondence about newsletter; continuing education seminars for alumni; Alumni: Allegheny Observatory, 1910-1941, Biophysics, Chemistry, 1946-1959, Geology, Mathematics, 1921-1958, Physics, and Psychology, 1949-1959
- Alumni, 1964-1967 (Box 10, Folder 83)
  Alumni and community relations; solicitation for funds; correspondence on George M. Shaw gift of Florida shells; draft copy of Natural Sciences Newsletter for Fall 1967; correspondence about solicitation of funds from DNS alumni.
- Annual reports, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  Annual reports for 1956/1957, 1957/1958, and 1961/1962.
- Auxiliary Enterprises, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 85)